Oh vasilieva suitum daivam comes a
charnel ramadan 'm dave aqui para mon
andum krishna monday jagadguru in the
second chapter of the bhagavad-gita the
subject of karma yoga has started Shri
Krishna has taught Gianni yoga the
nature of the self that I am the
absolute existence consciousness bliss
this has been taught and as a means to
the realization of that absolute Karma
Yoga has now been introduced we were on
verse 40 we had done a verse 40 and now
41 see Shri Krishna is making a case for
karma yoga what is the necessity of this
practice what is the practice is going
to start we know in general what he's
going to talk about how to spiritualize
our actions and how do you do that we
also know that what the advice would be
to connect it to God instead of thinking
that the primary motive being our own
selfish fulfillment of our own selfish
desires I am doing this action as a
worship of God this is going to be the
attitude for a karma yogi so that's what
he's going to teach do an action for as
our ship of God if you are a devotee
though it the same thing can be done as
I am doing this selflessly for the
welfare of others without bringing even
bringing God into the equation so people
might ask that if I don't believe in God
so can I do karma yoga yes you can
that's also possible and Shri Krishna
talks about that also but I don't
believe in God is not to my credit so if
you if you have some kind of faith in
God it's good you can put that to use
connect it to Karma Yoga do your actions
as a worship of God
and the second aspect of karma yoga is
that without a desire for what is called
the fruits of action that means I am NOT
doing it for what I'll get out of it
though once I perform the actions the
fruits will come the results will come
of themselves but I'm not doing it
primarily for that anymore
earlier I was doing it primarily for
that but now I'm doing it primarily as a
spiritual practice and of course results
will come yes in fact in Vedanta which
is almost nothing new so the roots of
everything that is taught
down to the to the present age the seed
of that the roots of that they all run
back to the Vedas to the Upanishads you
can trace it back but definitely sri
krishna's teaching of karma yoga and the
bhagavad-gita was a turning point it was
a major contribution so the contribution
is where he emphasized it and the
methodology and the way he taught it and
what great importance he gave to it so
that way sri sri krishna's genuine
contribution
new approach is there shri krishna was a
great teacher of karma thousands of
years ago and in this age it swami
vivekananda who again is reham phasis
that how do you spiritual eyes your your
daily life yes
yes yes yes yes if you notice that's
exactly what I have said karmayoga
as a as a means - it means - what did I
mention the structure of southerner ones
here last time that the matrix yes this
is what he's referring to so you can
difficut the matrix in mind you can
understand these comments this comment
is according to Shankara stinking Adi
Shankaracharya is thinking the matrix is
if you've got it written down somewhere
yes yes if you see the problem solution
and Method notice the teaching of of
Sankhya that means the teaching of the
nature of the self was that you are
brahman you are the absolute that should
solve the problem if I am existence
consciousness place
what problem actually remains if I'm
really convinced about that if it's
clear to me but the problem is it's not
at all clear to me I don't realize it at
all
the problem is Agana ignorant then the
method is gana yoga Shravana one Ananda
didn't listen to it study it engage with
it
reasoning and meditate upon it till it
becomes clear that's not working then
what is the problem that the mind is
scattered the mind is impure that is
what the commentator is talking about if
the mind is scattered and impure what
will happen at that stages I'm hearing
about it
I am reasoning I'm asking the questions
I'm memorizing the verses I'm even
trying to meditate after it after after
a fashion but it remains it's not a
direct living realization that's what's
called parotia parroquia means beyond
directrix
perience it remains as something that I
have read I have heard and I feel I have
people at this stage people will say I
understand intellectually but then
immediately the teacher knows the nature
of the problem this is where the problem
lies
I understand intellectually but then
krishna says all right
verse 39 let's start I understand the
problem the remedy is here and that's
true for most of us almost all of us
Vivekananda he says you can imagine as
chucklebunny says that I know where the
shoe pinches so we come down to our
daily like our life as we are leading it
Arjuna's life our life what we are doing
in life how do you spiritual eyes that
there is a need for that what is the
need the need is that without that
enlightenment is not possible for most
of us but theoretically you must leave a
little option for there for the rare few
who don't need all this Vedanta will of
course say that such people have already
done karma yoga and the past lives so
they are equipped for enlightenment
direct enlightenment ended those
fortunate few but otherwise most of us
we have to go through a graded course of
spiritual practice and that starts here
so he's making a case for karma yoga
what why is it necessary 41st verse
verse i ahte Mecca Budi verse aha Mika
Budi a guru nanaka karoon and and bahu
Shahen antoshka bahu shaka yun antoshka
buddhaya Vasari naam buddha yoga Vasari
naam so he says to Arjuna in this there
is a single one pointed determination
the thoughts of the irresolute are many
branched and infinite so the first
argument argument for spiritual practice
karma yoga here he means the entire
range of spiritual practice including of
course transformation of our work into
spiritual practice all kinds of
spiritual practice have for the first
most important argument for that is one
word focus focus the word he has used
here is a technical term varisai at
Makaha booty we have a sigh at Mecca
Buddha means one pointed clarity
conviction about spiritual life one
might have clarity about many things I'm
clear that I want to be a millionaire
and clear I want to be the next
Hollywood star so that's the kind of
clarity and it helps if you're really
clear about something is clear the decks
for action but here he means clarity
about spiritual life so what what is
this clarity a one pointed clarity about
spiritual life my goal in life is
enlightenment doesn't mean that have to
become a monk or something like that I
might or I might not but ultimately my
purpose in life is enlightenment God
realization this is real this is
worthwhile this is what I'm going to
pursue this is the highest thing open to
me this is the noblest endeavor of human
civilization is search for spiritual
enlightenment if I am a seeker and we
all are you wouldn't be here otherwise
you wouldn't even think of yourself as a
seeker but you are there's a whole range
there's a spectrum depending on
intensity and how advanced we are but we
are all speakers we are all seekers
they're all seekers I remember as a
young monk as a novice I used to ask
lots of questions so those who have
questions never don't feel bad and one
day I asked this Swami the monkey in
charge of the abbot of the monastery
Swami I bother you with so many question
don't you feel I mean from your point of
view isn't it irritating you must have
heard these questions so many times and
so many you know you've been a monk for
more than 50 years now so you know his
answer was illuminating he said no why
should I get irritated we are all
walking on the same path that's a very
interesting thing we are all doing the
same thing we are we are researching the
same we are in the same project together
so why should I get irritated you're
talking about what I am interested in he
didn't see all these things he just said
no why should I get irritated we are all
walking in the same path so that one
pointed conviction
my aim is God realization my aim is
Nirvana moksha salvation whatever you
call it interestingly enough Vedanta
would say that is our aim whether you
say it or not even the man who's trying
to make a million bucks on Wall Street
even the person who is a drug addict who
is or just your common man on the street
just trying to do muddle his way through
life doing his or her best in life all
of us whatever we are doing no matter
how confused no matter how determined in
life no matter how materialistic or
spiritual we are trying to find
fulfilment happiness in the best way
that we can this primal urge overcoming
suffering and finding satisfaction
fulfillment happiness this is the goal
now there is a wise way of doing it
which is spirituality that is the claim
of all the religions of the world
there's a wise way of doing it and
there's another wise way of doing it
which is what the rest of humanity is
doing now what Shri Krishna is saying
karma yoga starts with first step is
declare it at least to yourself I am a
spiritual seeker yeah I am no not like
that not one of the 10 things to do pick
up
milk and remember to reply to emails and
do a little bit of Vedanta not like that
I I am primarily a spiritual seeker
that's my definition that's how I define
myself so the comment is the one I'm
holding here is three that Swami's come
into becoming truly the commentators put
a very beautiful spin on this
the Streeter Swami he gives a devotional
approach to it what is via Vasai Atma
Kabaddi one pointed conviction clarity
about spiritual life in terms of
devotion beautiful thing has said here
Versailles at Mecca this restore means
Parameshwara bhakti I ever drew venturi
Shami eighty miss joy at Mecca Ava Aiken
styie vibhuti bhavati simple Sanskrit by
the grace of Bhagavad Parameshwara by
the grace of the lord by the grace of
God I shall certainly cross the ocean of
trance migratory XP existence I shall
certainly get freedom liberation moksha
salvation certainly this will happen
this he says one pointed conviction
clarity this is what is meant by we have
a sight my cup of tea
my goal is liberation and I and my
support is the grace of God God is my
support and nothing else this kind of
clearing of the decks for action in my
life does this not mean that I will
become a monk or something sounds like
that
not necessarily Arjuna continued to be a
warrior so this message has been
received by people across the ages and
they continue to do what they're doing
but their entire orientation about why
they are doing what they're doing is
changed its changed and it also makes it
very clear once you have a high goal in
life a clear goal in life decision
making also becomes very clear should I
do this or should I not do it should I
go there should I meet this person this
is what I want to do in life
all those things
become very clear once you have a clear
purpose in life in any field anybody who
has done anything great they have this
overwhelming concentration of effort
somebody said beautifully whether it is
Einstein or whether it is the Buddha or
whoever it is and I we all had this one
thing in common we all have 24 hours in
a day the difference between me and them
is what they did with those 24 hours
anything and generally people who have
achieved something great in life they do
that one thing most of the time even in
management science they tell us that 80%
of the results come from the 8020 rule
80% of the results come from 20% of our
work of all the things that we do it's
just 20% 1/5 of our activities which
give 80% of the results in our life that
means the rest of the activities is I
won't say wasteful but not really
productive and so you should concentrate
on that part of your life which is most
closely connected to your goal in life
your purpose in life that's the that's
the advantage of having a great purpose
overwhelming purpose in life and here
you don't have to ask what should be my
purpose in life we're telling you God
realization however you understand it
moksha liberation and you are in very
good company whether it is Buddha or
Krishna or Christ you're in good company
so this is the in fact the wisest
recommendation of all civilizations
across time that the highest thing that
you can aspire for is spiritual
liberation how it has been understood
different depends under the religions
and on the philosophies in fact Swami
Vivekananda would say I have a have a
goal I have a high goal in life and he
would say it should be your know your
own highest goal notice the words your
own highest so whose goal is it
it's mine like the Buddha said do
something not because you have been told
believe it not because you have been
told to believe it not because you have
read it that it is so not because your
elders have said it because you have
examined it and found it to be true
and good you found something to be true
and good therefore believe in it
therefore practice it in your lives so
it should be your own listen to
everybody attend all the classes read
all the books but it should be something
that you you own it yourself you feel
that I want this from your heart and
then the question would be that I have
so many things that I feel are my own
that I like which one it teenagers often
say there many things that I like and
watch it on TV I want to be like this
person or that person
I want to do this so all of those things
appeal to be especially when you are
young many things appeal to you so so
I'm really kind that says the highest
among each of them whatever your heart
says I want these things examine them
and see which is the noblest which is
the highest often the highest or noblest
would mean something that is of great
good to you and all to everybody else
often it is something that is extolled
praised greatly in our civilization so
your own highest goal we used to tell
students in the back in India that you
should have a goal in your life and I
remember the way I would tell it to them
is there would be students and there
would be monks present I would say look
if I asked you what is your goal in life
I'm sure I'm sure you can give it a
lecture on what should be our goal in
life but what is your goal in life right
now if I ask you most of you will sort
of scratch your heads um nothing
specific I mean I have my day to day
targets to do to-do list but overall I
don't know just make it through I kiss
from day to day you most of you would
say that and then I would point to the
monks and the novices would be sitting
there I said if you ask these people who
are wearing the orange robe or the white
of the novices if you ask them from the
from the youngest novice to the senior
most monk if you ask them this one
question what is your goal in life all
of them will immediately say yes we have
a goal in life and it is realization of
God in our order the goal is for your
own liberation and for the welfare of
the world for enlightenment freedom
salvation whatever you call it and for
the good of the world now that that's
what this dress stands for I have a
spiritual goal that's the declaration
that's ever the dress transform and this
is what krishna says you don't have to
put on a fancy dress somebody asked me i
think it is in holly it was in Hollywood
I was walking down Hollywood Boulevard
towards the library and somebody said
[Music]
why are you wearing an orange bedsheet
or something like
[Music]
no it is it is somewhere not in
Hollywood in Hollywood somebody start
being said I like it you don't have to
put on an orange bedsheet bedsheet but
as the saying in India goes you have to
color your mind Orange that means man
wrong ayah that there's a saying in
India that Oh yogi what a mistake you
have made you have colored your clock
but not your mind that means yogi you
have put on the cloth of a monk but you
haven't made your mind a monk of a monk
so you have invited made a great mistake
so we shall all over here see Christmas
is the mind of a spiritual seeker we
have a sigh at Makka booty one pointed
clarity conviction I am a spiritual
seeker and that's my goal
so my success and failure will I will
measure according to that there's any
old saying in India a rainy day is not a
bad day it's a bet it's an unfortunate
Dave and I forget to take the name of
Hari I'm gonna forget to take the name
of God that's the unfortunate day a
rainy day is not an unfortunately it's
coming tomorrow snowy day
[Music]
okay one more point here he says those
whose minds are not one-pointed their
minds are multi-pronged they have
multiple desires and they run after
those desires so bahu shahe the minds
are divided into multiple streams and
the energies flow out year after year
life goes by like that giving up these
multiple projects in life you will still
do something you'll have a job you take
care of it do your duties definitely
like Arjuna is being asked to do is duty
but seeking for seeking for fulfilment
in the world from the world going about
the world with a begging bowl give me
happiness a couple of words of praise a
little success a little little happiness
there little pleasure there going around
with the begging bowl to the world that
should stop giving up this project of
finding happiness in sense pleasures so
there is an interesting point here
notice how the spiritual disciplines the
five fundamental practices in Vedanta
and similarly it is in yoga also ahimsa
drama teria satya asteya Aparri caja
non-violence self-control specially
control of lust truth non-stealing non
acceptance of gifts so these are
practices for a yogi but consider how
giving up these these negativities all
of them have the same form what I mean
is this one one a teacher pointed this
out all spiritual practices have the
same effect peace serenity quietude
calmness peace
what I mean by that is this violence
anger it can have many farms depending
on whether you are irritated with your
neighbor irritated that well or angry
with politics or furious at yourself or
angry with the kids it could be of many
many many forms many farms many textures
anger irritation fury but giving up
anger giving up violence in thought word
and deed is of only one form that is
peace do you see what I mean they
actually doing that in life that means
giving free expression to anger and
violence can take many forms anger and
violence can take many forms
angry thought angry word and depending
on the person you are angry with the
situation you're angry with many many
many endless forms what he says bahu
shaka divided into many forms but giving
up anger and violence that give him
subtracting of non-violence it is only
one form peace sense pleasures are many
types depending on the sense objects
there's a desire for a cookie forum for
a movie for the company of a friend for
all kinds so many objects of pleasure in
the world and as many objects of
pleasure so many different types of
enjoyment and desires so desires are
multiple for sense pleasure but the
practice of brahmacarya giving up
letting go of that is of one nature only
peace Shanthi similarly truth falsities
of many types they say the truth is
wonderful lies are many or chesterton
put it very beautifully he said there's
only one way to stand up straight the
many ways to fall down lies are many and
as we if I tell lies the the uneasiness
anxiety the complications in my life
will be
various sorts endlessly multiplying
various sorts but giving up lies is a
one-shot only piece you see where I'm
going with this all the vices are of
multiple sorts all passions and worldly
desires are of an enormous multiplicity
but giving them up while giving them up
why because I die it's not no longer I
don't think that I am going to get
permanent satisfaction or joy in them
that's no longer my primary pursuit so
giving that up in sanskrit thiago is of
one type only peace that peace and this
one pointed desire for God realization
the one pointed pursuit of spirituality
they go together without that peace did
this one pointedness will not come I
cannot have a hundred worldly projects
running and 101 will be realized God it
won't work those have to be put aside
put aside means the formula swami
vivekananda gives neither seek nor avoid
life will present you with plenty of
things to do don't for your days will be
occupied and as it is even without
adding two things you will not you will
still keep running out of time I
remember seeing this cartoon I mentioned
it and the Father time there is a
cartoon a father time and next to it is
mother not enough time mother is running
around with kids and lots of chores to
do and sings like that so mother not
enough time so what the world will
present you with plenty of things to do
your life will be over full so don't
worry that what will I do if I give up
all those things so peace giving up
those worldly pursuits the result is of
one type only that is peace that peace
and the focus on spirituality they are
one and the same
another point Swami
this is a point that Swami Rama sook
does demon made in his book on the Gita
commentary on the Gita I haven't found
it elsewhere but it's a very subtle and
interesting points I'll put it before
you
he says contrast it with Gianni yoga
what preceded earlier in Gyana yoga
knowledge is primary one must
intuitively grasp that I am the Atman
once that clarity comes that Atman you
will see inside and outside in every
experience it's the same Atman same
awareness same consciousness same being
we read that in the sixteenth verse of
the Bhagavad Gita nacet Ovid deity of
hatha if you remember that isness
everywhere it's there so in every
experience will recognize that and the
serenity of mind the focus of mind
concentration will come after that
automatically it will come in ghana yoga
he says in karma yoga bhakti yoga and
raja yoga the process is reversed first
a peace of mind and concentration must
come then only enlightenment will will
follow after that so bhakti yoga starts
with this way of a PSYOP make abuti
let me repeat again the contrast between
the two approaches in karma yoga bhakti
yoga and raja yoga which is going to
speak about now it starts with a
clearing of the decks I want to give up
all other pursuits and pursuits personal
spirituality one-pointed clarity and
conviction it starts with this then only
the spiritual progress is possible this
is the normal way to approach it
but there is a direct approach which was
talked about first there instead of
talking about these things
shri krishna pointed out the nature of
the absolute if one can grasp it one is
fortunate among the fortunate few who
can grasp this then this one pointedness
follows by itself you see it's like this
I look at the necklace and the bangle
and the ring and if I've understood what
is gold then whatever I see as
see gold when I see the necklace l see
gold when I see the bangle l see gold
when I see the ring I will see gold
one-pointedness one-pointedness has come
instead of multiplicity I'm seeing the
one though I'm seeing all that all the
ornaments do you remember the the
example of the ornaments and gold the
enlightened person in whatever
experience men women children
good and bad in youth and old age in
success and failure it is the same
existence consciousness place with
different names and forms so one
pointedness stability automatically
comes there once that is grasped but
it's very difficult to grasp it to begin
with so the other way is spiritual
practice having known that theoretically
now they get into spiritual practice
proper she starts with karma yoga and so
we have a sigh of Mecca booty this one
pointed clarity and conviction is this
distinction did it make sense
I am NOT founded anywhere but it said in
the subtle but important point which Ram
soup does she points out another place I
think it was Swami forget one of the
direct disciples may be sorrow Garland's
you're somebody who writes there are
actually two broad spiritual paths one
is the path of Gianni yoga the path of
knowledge the other one is the path of
action devotion meditation karma yoga
bhakti yoga and Raja yoga if you look at
it from a metal sense if you step back
and see the the approach there are these
two approaches one depends upon effort
it's a graded progress step by step you
go that is karma yoga bhakti yoga Raja
yoga the other one is a direct cutting
through to the reality yes
[Music]
yes yes yes we are not we are not
already Saints that's what I mean so we
are we are moving towards that for for
us all these practices in fact the rest
of the Gita are in spiritual life what
is spiritual life how do I live and how
do I practice spirituality all of that
but we must make allowance for it's rare
few who are like that it is a
possibility such people are there and we
all have to go to that point yes yes
isn't bhakti yes but remember the
framework that we are taking here is is
in a very broad sense Advaita Vedanta
non-dual Vedanta so there bhakti is sort
of you know knowledge is privileged
above devotion because in this framework
what what they will say bhakti towards
God devotional love and surrender
towards God will ultimately lead you to
that realization also because God will
give you that knowledge whatever is
needed God will add on to you but that's
still a little indirect because you are
taking from the individual to God to the
absolute and the GaN Yoga is to the
absolute directly you are Brahman but
it's all in the paradigm of Ghani away
if you're coming from the paradigm of
bhakti then Mukti is obviously the most
direct path there is a devotional
paradigm where God exists I exist and my
relation to God is one of devotion and
surrender
that's it stories finished but Advaita
Vedanta says there is something beyond
that beyond God and the individual
ji-won Ishwara there
the absolute brahman and real freedom is
realizing your identity with absolute I
am Brahman am Brahma ask me then what is
the role of devotion in that that's what
we are coming to karma yoga bhakti yoga
Raja Yoga are all helps secondary means
to the attainment of knowledge this
commentator which he said that until you
practice these things that knowledge
which I taught in taught you earlier
that knowledge will remain parochial
Jana secondary knowledge indirect
knowledge it becomes direct knowledge
with the practice of these things do you
see that do different paradigms one must
it's complicated but one must be big
enough to see different paradigms the
spiritual life is vast see what's
written there just above you truth is
one sages call it variously we are all
talking about the same thing but one may
look at it from a knowledge perspective
one may look at it from a purely
devotional perspective in our order we
look at it from knowledge and devotion
Sri Ramakrishna I was just reading Swami
Turia and the ji says in this age Sri
Ramakrishna primarily taught Gianna
Mishra bhakti devotion with knowledge
knowledge and devotion but there are
paths of pure devotion and as there are
paths of pure knowledge if I were
talking about the path of pure knowledge
I would have stopped at 3740 before
starting this this all of this you are
Brahman realized that what's your
problem and there are teachers who do
that there are teachers who do that the
so called direct path teachers there are
some especially in this country and
naturally United States people are
impatient realization here and now so
there are the teachers who teach the
direct path and it's it's very
attractive because of two reasons one it
says one is it seems instant now second
it seems effortless nothing just I have
to realize it I have to know it
knowing it doesn't seem so difficult
there's a catch there but but the
problem with that is often you will
notice the teachings of these direct
path teachers I will not take some names
some of them are actually genuine many
of them are not they don't know what
they're talking about but something
because it's easy to talk but some of
them are genuine even the ones who are
genuine in many cases you will find they
have themselves pursued this graded path
for a long time some form of meditation
some form of devotion some form many
different practices they have been
inquiring for years and years and years
then they make a breakthrough and then
they say oh it's so clear and direct let
me teach that but what they are making
mistake is to for them to come to this
understanding it's so clear and direct
and evident they had to go through a lot
and which if the other person in front
of you has not gone through that they
will just look at you with a blank
expression Mandi when you say it's here
right now don't you see it huh what yes
so a graded approach is good I was
reading Swami Torian and I admire
missing Torian and Izzy his birthday's
day after tomorrow so look at the
difference it will identify easily with
it he talks he says when swami
vivekananda would say i he identified
with the consciousness in everybody he
did not the words he uses is he did not
identify with the oopah the apothem it's
body mind I as consciousness in
everybody and then Swami Torian and the
ji who is himself a great non duelist
but he says that does not come so
naturally to us so I like this that I
surrender everything to God in Bengali
said what our mother Hina that doesn't
come so easily to us so for us I
surrender to God everything to God
though is a great way than thin non
duelist then somebody asking the
question so for a devotee if somebody
who loves God a dualistic approach is it
good to study these non-dualistic texts
he asked this question and I have been
asked his question I was very interested
to see what's Swamy Torian and I said
and you know what he said he said for
the devotee who continuously surrenders
everything to God and says thou alone
not me what difference is between that
is there between that and advaitha what
difference is where is the difference
between that and advaitha and non
duality and then he goes on to say Sri
Ramakrishna is to say tie the knowledge
of advaitha to the hem of your cloth and
then do whatever you like whatever you
like means you can take the devotees
path also you can take the path of
service you can remain immersed in
meditation whatever you like you can be
dynamic and active you can withdraw to a
cave and sit in serene meditation you
can be an ecstatic devotee it can be a
combination of all of these which we
have a current themself alright let's go
on before we go on before the actual
teaching of karma yoga the other kind of
karma which we are used to Shri Krishna
is pointing out the danger in that the
problem in what we are doing right now
now the Karma that we are doing has two
aspects one of which is we are very
familiar with to the worldly Karma the
work that we do in family and community
and career all of that whatever we are
doing what we call work that is karma in
sanskrit lo Kika karma day-to-day
activities are our our daily activities
but there was another there's another
kind of karma which is yd karma the
religious work that's also work so in
Krishna Sri Krishna's time people
ordinary people in the world they did
both kinds of work one is the daily
duties of life also religious rites in
those days it meant Vedic sacrifices
these days we do puja we go to temples
and do puja and all of that in those
days it was the fire sacrifice is
prescribed by the Vedas
all of this work whether this worldly or
otherworldly whether secular or
religious all of this work Srikrishna
classifies as ordinary karma Sakuma
Carmody the one connecting feature of
them is that they're prompted by worldly
desire this worldly desire otherworldly
desire in this world I want money and
pleasure and power and fame
therefore I work and in the other world
I want to go to heaven and I have a good
time
therefore I work what means I do
religious rituals now the next three
verses are about those religious rituals
but they equally apply to our worldly
activities also and this is not
something he's recommending he is
condemning them he's saying these are
not spiritual
let alone the worldly activities
prompted by desire but also the the
Vedic of the religious activities
prompted by desire they are religious
but not spiritual so look at the three
tiers he has established worldly worldly
religious and spiritual we have to read
40 to 43 and 44 together Yami mom
pushbutton bottom Yami mom pushbutton
bottom Provident OB / cheetah Provident
of a pasta with the water-rat of Part V
devavrata Sparta non Yoda sthiti Wadena
nana defeat evil dina Kamat mana vergara
kamat mana swagger para janma karma
polyp rodham janma karma paulo Pradhan
kriya vishesha bulam kriya vishesha
bogus for yoga team pretty bogus warrior
gratine pretty bogus warrior prasat UNAM
bow - warrior prasad Onam taya opposite
Ajit some day operator cheat some give
us our yacht Mika booty where was I at
Mecca booty somato Navi deity Samad of a
deity what he's going to say now the
last line where was I at make about this
Ahmad who Nvidia is the point that
Versailles at Mecca with the one pointed
clarity and conviction about spiritual
life is essential for spiritual life or
for spiritual practice that is not
possible if somebody is involved in such
things
what are such things he talks about one
side only the Vedic rituals the
religious rituals but also it includes
the worldly activities what are they
Yami mom pushbutton watch am prevalent
which ovipositor be unwise talking about
the flowery language of the Vedas which
tell you such-and-such heavens are
waiting for to be attained please
perform these rituals and give me give
the priest his commission and then after
death the merit you have earned by
religious activity will take you to
heaven every religion as this at one
time the I think the Catholic Church is
to sell indulgences that is one of the
things that I think Martin Luther
protested against so I have committed a
lot of sins suppose and I'm going to die
I'm afraid of going to hell now can I
give an donation to the church and the
church will write me a letter saying
that will give him a pass on this so
every religion has this kind of thing
that after death whether I deserve it or
not I'm going to have a wonderful time
there'll be a heaven where there is no
suffering no hunger and thirst
all pleasures are instantaneously
fulfilled
and so in Hinduism also you have not won
heaven multiple heavens depending on
your credit worthiness how much merit
have accumulated you go get to go to
different heavens we had a wonderful
Swami Swami mr. Chanin DG who
established the vedanta work in south
africa many decades ago he came to us he
also visited he I never met him but I've
heard about him from senior monks and
devotees so he was a remarkable person
by all accounts he was a disciple of
swami sivananda a great way don t non
duelist but also a great yogi who
actually had who did her to Yoga is
rarely in among the monks of our order
and who had attained certain even
sydney's some spiritual powers I am so
on great scholar and an extraordinary
teacher so as you will see from this
example he gives he gave an example to
explain this kind of teaching of the
Vedas remember the Vedas have two parts
broadly speaking karma-kanda jnana-kanda
Gianna con des Vedanta gana Conda means
the portion dealing with spiritual
knowledge the portion dealing with
spiritual knowledge that's the
culmination the final teachings of the
Vedas that is spirituality and that is
found in the texts called Upanishads but
apart from that the vast bulk of the
Vedas they contain teachings about
religious rituals most of which are not
practiced anymore by Hindus modern
Hindus have replaced those by modern
rituals called poojas but the ancient
Vedic rituals they were meant for the
same old things and I'll give you the
exact the exact quotations from the
Vedas where there are such promises as
bris T comma Y Zeta those if you desire
rainfall sacrifice sacrifice unto the
gods if we desire Putrajaya if you
desire a child especially a male child
in those days yes they were very
patriarchal and misogynistic but
sacrifice unto the gods then saga comma
if you desire heaven after death
sacrifice unto the gods and so on and
the and the sacrifices were of various
types depending upon your income range
there's something to suit capacity
enough to take whatever you got so you
make your place in heaven
Swami initiations he gives an example of
that he this beautiful example to
explain that see you earn this merit
depending on your good works your
religious rituals and meritorious works
and you go to heaven but whatever is
earned by work is limited so it's not
endless heaven after a long long period
of time your merit will be exhausted
your credit cards will be maxed out and
then you'll be tossed out of heaven you
go back you get back go back to earth
your older karma takes hold of you and
you are born again in some family and
you carry on with your spiritual
evolution but you have a what is it
called furlough like a break in heaven
and multiple heavens and it's all
subject to an end it comes to an end so
the example is this so I'm initiations
he he said it's like when I come from
South Africa to India I booked a ticket
from Johannesburg to Mumbai and it takes
money so I have to collect the money for
the ticket and I booked the ticket and
then when I get into the aeroplane there
is the air hostess who says come come
this is your seat now he's actually
literally translating from the Vedas the
descriptions like this after death the
after giving up the body the soul
sukshma sharir did achieve Atman is
greeted by heavenly messengers who say
AE AE
a shava socrata secretest Alok aha
I forgot the exact term this is the
meritorious world this is the world you
have earned by your merit come come and
enjoy so the air hostesses come come
here is your seat and then I strap
myself into this seat and you go high
and high higher thirty thousand five
the captain says we are flying at 30,000
feet
and then there is this wonderful food
and there is a movie to be seen and so
it's so nice and by the time you're
getting used to it in the city I could
live like this this is very nice
the captain makes the announcement they
decide descending into Mumbai it's the
temperature outside is a hundred degrees
in the shade and 100% humidity and you
say no no I want to stay here well we
hope you'll fly with Air India again and
here back to earth now this is the Vedic
conception of heaven nothing spiritual
about it that that particular it's a
kind of otherworldly pleasure and so he
says the ones who get enticed by the
flowery words promised in the Vedas you
might ask where does a religious sticks
why would they do this in fact they're
to this religion has these two aspects
of a religion where it serves our needs
in this world and the next I want to be
happy here I want to be wealthy here I
want to be healthy I want my children to
be to do well can God and religion
helped me most people use religion for
this purpose and that's what the Vedas
also said you want health you want
prosperity do these things so a moral
sustainable kind of life which make
gives you worldly happiness but he's
strictly limited it will all come to an
end there's no other way and it also
promises you other worldly happiness a
refined version of worldly happiness
that also comes to an end it's only when
one graduates out of kindergarten
religious kindergarten and says how many
times do I have to go through this why
go through this you may say I don't
remember any of it it would be nice if I
remember it going to heaven and all of
that you do not as memory but as some
scar as tendon
see the reason why you are here today
and I am here today this is not a very
pretty picture for any of us we want the
truth
Who am I what is the meaning of all of
this it is there any permanent solution
to the to the cycle of life life and
death we are searching for Nirvana
moksha enlightenment freedom so when you
graduate to this higher class then the
Upanishads come and say they condemn
this what Krishna is doing
so that is not for you we have got
something better for you so worldly
karma or other worldly karma is to be
replaced by Karma Yoga and Sri Krishna
is setting the stage for that why did
the Vedas ate vader's know that we want
enjoyment we will do it in an immoral
way to stop that that's destructive for
us and for everybody else so the way it
is prescribed a moral sustainable way
not just the way this every religion
does that you want money you want
pleasure you want power nothing wrong
with it at all but stay within the
limits of truth and self-control earn
money only what you have earned things
like that all religions do it our urge
for worldly enjoyment the religions seem
to support it but only because we want
it and once we graduate from it then
they will show us the real thing which
is God realization enlightenment need
one or whatever you call it now near the
spirit of Athena these pro pounders of
the Vedic ritual ISM they say that there
is nothing else there is this world
which you are living in and after death
there is that word okay that sounds
great but just a minute after that after
that this is this world again and then
the next world again okay then I don't
want this I'll do whatever I want then
there is the other world for you
that other place with you and in
Hinduism there is not one hell there
multiple heads but only there is no
eternal hell and they are basically all
what the results of our own naughtiness
basically so the Vedas say if you want
worldly
distance and otherworldly existence then
do it in a moral way in an ethical way
in a sustainable way but truly wise if
you are you will go beyond this kammath
Manas warga para those who are desirous
of heaven come Atman are full of desires
in this world in the next world
janma karma philip Rodham they engage in
this worldly activities secular
activities and religious activities
which the activities are karma secular
and religious pala pala means result the
result will be this life and the next
life you will get the results janma
means birth after birth birth and death
cycle will continue propelled the fuel
is karma karma is nothing but
cause-and-effect causality Kriya avishay
shava hula and is a whole range it's a
supermarket of Vedic rituals what do you
want everything is available and this is
all for baggage for yoga Timothy for
enjoyment I share your glory and
enjoyment power glory wealth and so this
sounds great if I taught be careful
there's another kind you know who say
can't I have both yeah I like it Swami
what you're talking about enlightenment
is one I want that but this also is a
great writer I can can I have both of
them know are and know they are
fundamentally contradictory this is I
want to remain as a separate individual
and I want to go from enjoyment to enjoy
party hopping from one party to another
party to another party I want my life to
be one long party so that that's the
model the paradigm I'm working with and
this is something very different I give
all that up to enjoy peace and bliss in
the company of God if you are a devotee
or in the realization of who we really
are
the the witness self the pure
consciousness the absolute so there did
they - do not go together
one is within karma one is beyond Karma
yes
yes scattered in the four Vedas yes yes
each Veda has a karma kanda ritualistic
portion and AG anaconda a knowledge
portion contradictory min one only in
one sense the later portion will
repudiates the earlier portion if you
ask why should it be so as I just
explained it's because we want it if the
Vedas had their way they would take a
straight to spirituality the book that
tried that have you noticed when
Buddha's teaching was centrally about
moksha born in Varna
it became a heavily monastic religion
but ultimately the result was not good
for India when thousands and thousands
of people were not really cut out for
the ultimate spiritual goal not cut out
for monastic life it became a
prestigious thing to be a Buddhist monk
or a nun and they gave up their worldly
life and they all went to the
monasteries society collapsed and the
monasteries they cook the quality there
went down all sorts of malpractice is
entered into monastic life anyway yes
yes absolutely all you the bigger
Upanishads they also have rituals but
they just show that ritual as a person
as a spirit prepare a tree spiritual
practice not for attaining worldly goals
but for for pure it will make it clear
if you have worldly goals then this or
other worldly goals then this very
ritual will give you those goals but you
will not get spirituality if you want
spirituality then this very ritual will
give you purity of mind see there
somebody asked this Karma Yoga is it
krishna's invention no it is actually
there in dopes initials these rituals
which are supposed to be part of karma
kanda they are also found in the Vedas
in Cuddapah nation in the new
Phoenicians in canto Benicia there is a
ritual which is taught by amar
educator it's a kind of a Vedic fire
sacrifice no details are given there now
what the open assured wants to say is if
you want heaven heavenly existence you
can use this ritual collect enough
credit merit and after death you go to
heaven but you will not be spiritual he
will not get enlightenment but if you
want enlightenment then this same ritual
will help you to get purification of
mine it should not want the worldly or
otherworldly results then so the same
work you see the root of karma yoga is
there the same action can make you
worldly if your goal is worldly the same
action can set you free from action can
make you spiritual if your goal is
spiritual that's the the seed of karma
yoga right there of course Krishna will
give a much more developed teaching here
yes what one has to be cleared there see
in many cases the explicit need is not
there but we generally have the needle
till it's like this let things go well
for me let things go well for everybody
and often there is a element of fear
involved if I don't do it will something
bad happen to me that is a that is a
clear indicator that I have a some
amount of worldliness left in me I am
doing it for God realization God will be
pleased with me my beloved Lord will be
pleased with this worship that is karma
yoga whether it is worship or doing my
daily duties look at Arjuna he enters
into this battle for worldly reasons I
want the Kingdom I want to take revenge
on the evildoers that selfish actually
all justifiable but selfish worldly now
Krishna is saying do the same thing as
an offering to God
you have put me this is my in this
situation this is my duty I shall do it
what do I want I want God I don't want
this it will come of its own accord it
did the
Punda was one the battle they got the
kingdom all of that came but no longer
was it for that purpose anymore with
decay and karma becomes karmayoga
creation above alarm so many rituals
will be prescribed if you even nowadays
you go to a Hindu temple the priest will
have a whole menu of rituals for you to
perform one should look at the price
list before you go yes you had a
question yes it is true and your
question basically is is desire for God
also not a desire are you giving up all
desires when you when you say I want God
literally I want God is a desire so Sri
Ramakrishna gave the answer to that he
said desire for God is not to be counted
among other desires why because it roots
out all other desires
notice the desire for God is not a
desire if you put it in non-dualistic
terms it becomes even more clear I want
to realize my own true nature Atman
which is the Atman of everybody then I
become identified with everybody if you
actually look at the life of such a
person usually the life of such a person
will be one continuous self-sacrifice
does not want anything for oneself so
the person is transformed into a saint
it would be very different from
everybody else now what made this person
him or her become like this that I don't
want these worldly pursuits
I want to realize who I am you might say
even that is for yourself it is true but
then that self will be the capital S not
an individual self cut off from
everybody else if notice how if one
person becomes a saint and in
in person everybody else actually
benefits immediately everybody
surrounding that person everybody in
society they even the presence of such
Saints is a blessing to society so it's
not that they gain by themselves it is
everybody gains with the presence of
such people and they identify with
everybody they don't feel that ah now
I'm enlightened and you are fools no
they feel most ordinary they feel that I
am NOT God alone is that individual
identity either in devotion or in
knowledge individual identity is
submerged what is the harm in pursuing
worldly pleasure in success Bhavesh
warrior percept an entire apparatus at
Assam Versailles Africa Buddhism our own
of it here take those whose minds are
swept away a Purita means robbed stolen
swept away by this overwhelming desire
for pleasure were worldly success their
minds will never stabilise on God that
one pointed clarity conviction will not
come it will keep getting swept away you
keep getting swept away you see now you
understand what is the monastic life
basically it's just a formalization of
what is being taught here the dress the
codes the behavior we told do not mix
with worldly people those whose goals
are worldly do not mix with them why not
are they bad people no it's simply that
if if those desires those things again
we are rekindled within you they're
already there within us
rique indeed within you you will again
be swept away from your spiritual
conviction and it will be swept back
into the worldly path I know I remember
there's a number of such examples a monk
I remember he was a doctor before he
became a monk but he was what is called
an MBBS
do we have such a degree in USA what
would be equivalent in MD no but in
India also you have an MD which is above
a movie yeah so this monk a very nice
Swami is much more senior to me one day
he was posted to the our Hospital the my
hospital run by the monks in Calcutta we
have a big Hospital and one day I heard
he had left he had left the order
monastic order what happened now an MBBS
is actually a lower degree and MD is a
higher degree now when he's there as a
monk he's also working and serving the
patients and everything and he sees the
other doctors now there are these other
doctors who are well-known doctors or
famous doctors who are really rich and
they have flourishing practices and the
others it's a hospital after all so
other people are in all of them and this
poor monkey is working there and he with
them again again after some time a
desire grew too in his mind I should
also be an MD so he gave up the monastic
life and he said what is he doing he
enrolled in the MD course for for being
an MD you see how it gets covered over
again a monastic aspiration suddenly of
all the aspiration again is rekindled
yeah if you put you have to be very
careful where you put put it in sri
ramakrishna talked about the fence a new
sapling it needs to be fenced in because
he says otherwise the goats and cows
will come and eat it
but he says when it becomes a huge
banyan tree you said dear friends is not
required and in fact you can tie an
elephant to it nothing will happen to it
so when we begin our spiritual life
protect it protect this aspiration I've
seen it again and again I know this
couple in in California who are now
there they are really rich really
successful and spiritual
and they were telling me about their
plans how they will spend the time in
meditational and in-between the event
for the cruise and they came back and
all the time all the plans changed
why because on the cruise they met they
met these people who were richer than
them more successful than them and they
thought that maybe we want one more
mansion than the the latest luxury car
and this and that the desire of awakened
you may we may laugh at it but when it
is the desire comes and it is possible I
know I have the capacity I know I have
the money maybe a little more effort a
few more years of working and a few more
investments and I can get that mansion
then it takes possession of you it's
like a ghost you're you're bewitched
possessed by a ghost and what will
happen is 5-10 years of your life will
go away again before one swings back
into the to the this is how spiritual
evolution goes but one can shorten this
torturous process make a Vemma sciatica
body's very important is one takeaway
from this classes it's a lifetime's
decision to make I define myself as a
spiritual seeker you need not change
anything externally the external changes
will come slowly over time but make up
your mind from now on I am a spiritual
seeker whenever it comes you reaffirm
this it's not something that we have
done today and that's it every day is a
reaffirmation that I am a spiritual
seeker God is my very own my purpose in
life is enlightenment yes I want to be
happy and peaceful and blissful the way
I will do it is through spirituality
that is the wisest way of doing it I
will not mention my success and failure
in worldly terms anymore let it happen
don't measure your achievements in
worldly terms anymore your friends and
relatives who are on that path they will
go along in that path and they will have
they'll have our worldly achievements
accomplishments very good be happy for
them no regrets once you take this path
we have already seen some of
that that's enough the wise man the wise
person sees a little bit and understands
the rest of worldly life is like this
one person a devotee in Detroit he said
to me you know Swami how this
realization have come to this that
there's no end to this what I'm doing
he's in the corporate ladder it is a
very big multinational American company
so there's still a higher position to
achieve there is if you have a boat you
know you want a your own aeroplane and
then things like that is more and more
and more there's no end to it this is
just saying you know if even if you win
the right race you are a rat really make
up your mind very clearly once you do it
it's not very difficult at all what's
done is done
I have learned my lesson from that and
my purpose now is got realization it's
not very difficult not even asking you
to make a huge change in fact Arjuna
wanted to make a huge change I want to
give this all up and I become a monk
Krishna's is no no no wait a minute you
stay right where you are
keep doing right what you'd rather I
will show you how right here you can
become enlightened so that's the whole
grand topic of karma yoga the teaching
has not yet started but like a good
teacher
you say he's building up the base what
is the need for the teaching we realized
this today the need for Karma Yoga is
that one pointed clarity conviction it
won't come it won't be stable unless we
do karma away we'll see what what is to
be done if I'm not going to pursue
worldly goals and what am I going to
pursue what am I going to do with my
time and energy he'll tell you and if I
don't do that what's the harm so two
things krishna has said in the 41st
verse he said what is the purpose of
this and the 42nd 43rd and 44th if you
don't do it if you remain engaged in
worldly and other worldly activities as
we are right now what is the harm that's
what he pointed out Shawn dish
the shanti hurry he owned cats at sri
ramakrishna aparna must see even this
thing we chant sri ramakrishna eponymous
took we offered this at the defeat of
sri ramakrishna this is the Karma Yoga
actually we did all of this and for what
purpose
for the so that the Lord is pleased and
that's that's the philosophy of work